I see the surface of the Earth covered
with
flow and smeared with incense
powder it has the all the continents of
the planet and there's the Sun and the
Moon I picture it as an I picture it as
an enlightened
paradise and I offer to you you know may
all being to enjoy Paradise
so I don't know when I first started
studying Buddhism it was like everybody
talked about saving they didn't even
call it saving the world they said uh
what do they call
it know for all sensient beings you know
and
uh then you have this kind of image
that
uh I don't know somehow you become
enlightened and then you can snap your
fingers and everyone's okay or something
like that you know at the time I I felt
like that but then as I learned more and
more it's
like if you could learn to see how
things really work right if if you could
make uh money at
will or you could change People's Health
at
will
or everybody could have a good
relationship the relationship they
always want
if you if you had some kind of
understanding that
could could cause that and you could
spread it then you could save the that
would be saving the world got it then it
would be a paradise you see so
uh I feel like that we were in China and
uh lots of people were there hundreds
and hundreds of people thousands and
then
um we we would we would present all
these ideas about how things are coming
from you the pen and they would get it
and then we would say that applies to
money that applies to health that
applies to your partner and they would
get that and then we would we would pose
the question at some point this is all
communist Chinese people right at some
point we would
say uh what do you think would happen if
everybody thought this way and then uh
there's a you know as I said there's
like a a 30C pause and everybody in the
audience they kind of look up like this
you know how you look when you're
thinking you know you you go like this
so you see all the eyes go up towards
the
ceiling and then and then all the hands
would come up at the same time and
they'd say oh they'd be a perfect world
you know the world would be perfect you
know and these are people who just came
to their first T you know and they they
would get it you know so the thing
that the key that would allow all you to
make it happen in the world is emptiness
you see so if you you must grasp
emptiness then you can save the world
you see that's the only thing that lies
between us and a perfect world if people
understood emptiness
then everything would be Planet B okay
all
right so it's crucial this is crucial if
you're interested in saving the world if
you're interested
in uh stopping the pain of the world
then this is crucial this is it here we
go and people even people in the first
time in an audience who grew up in a
totally what do you call it uh secular
secular society they they would get it
like that you know so maybe because they
grew up in it second I don't know so
here we
[Music]
go we were talking about
say
to and we were talking about a
pen
so you look at a
and there's a feeling about where it
comes from right there's a feeling about
that it's out there and it comes from
itself and when you hold up a pen you're
not consciously thinking oh that's
coming from me right
so there's a way that this pen is
appearing to me there's something coming
from the pen towards me which is a a
false
appearance that it comes from itself
there's that kind of pen
there if if if your mind is in that mode
and
say if all you say is I ate L nothing
more if you are seeing things this way
and you say I ate lunch then you're
already in trouble okay you're you're
going to
die okay that makes you mortal that will
kill you eventually that will kill you
uh it's very powerful okay so he says
that that's what it means to be holding
to the
say me you
don't look into it MAA means you don't
investigate you don't analyze without
analyzing the question or without
looking into it if you say is the person
in the mirror Mike uh you can say yeah
that's Mike is this a
pen it is a pen that's not wrong
to say it's a pen is not
wrong without without investigating the
question of where it came from
ultimately it's a
pen just the
me that's coming from my
mind okay I like to do it with a pen
pretend that's mic
okay the mic is coming from from my mind
okay what do you mean the mic was coming
from my
mind this the last thing we always do in
China I tell Ningbo go go sit over there
and get the camera ready you know and
then I everybody's you know being
secular and uh and we're talking about
pens and money and and then I say the
last thing I always say is you know I
hold up the pen and then I put my arm
there and I say is it the
same you know what is this and then they
all they go then then you see this spark
in their eye something cuz we're all
Mortal right whe whatever country you
live in you're Immortal and then there's
a spark in there on there's this the
spark goes like this you know and then
it's all back to then we give
congratulations to the
organizer but
uh when when I say you just hold it up
and then there's this feeling that yeah
might might comes from here also the
mortality of his arm the blood vessel
the
skin the bone the the Mortal part are
are also coming from me the mortality of
it is coming from me right because I
haven't respected life enough okay so I
and if I had I would see something
different woof woof right and then try
to explain to a dog that this could have
been a
pen come from Planet B and sit in a room
of Planet a people and say
you knowy sitting in a bunch of you know
poodles and
say you
know you know not that's the
communication gap
between it's that serious you know to to
come to a room and say you don't have to
buy you don't have to use cars that
don't work you can take aspirins that
work every time you can arrange it so
you never have to take an aspin
uh people hear it and people process it
but people don't
really on a deep level I guess we're
just too used to living the other
way so it's kind of a huge leap for a
poodle to to write a
poem but we have to
try okay here we go
uh Simi if you just leave it at that
simeni means be satisfied with that let
it go at that
then you can say Mike goes Mike is going
to go home to his cabin and take a nap
uh I'm gon to stay I'm gonna
go the whole way that stuff works you
know people go people
come it's all cool it all it's all all
right you can understanding emptiness
doesn't mean you can't say I'm going to
walk home
today okay to think that you can't say
I'm going to walk home today if you
understand Emptiness is a mistake okay
you can say it you do go home you will
go home okay if your toilet work or not
I don't know
okay okay this is very difficult
we posited three states of mind that
were looking at Mike the first one
looked at Mike and said Mike is a
product of my the seeds in my
mind according to the degree of kindness
I have shown to others okay that was the
first one what was the second one was uh
I just look in the mirror and that's M
and I don't worry about it I'm not
worrying where it came from I'm just I'm
just shaving his face and I'm not like
analyzing where did he come from then
the third one was an active uh denial
that he could have come from
me is is is the is this pen made by seas
in your mind or by a pen
Factory see and your your immediate
reaction is uh pen
Factory and and then then you've drawn a
wrong now you're actively
wrong that's the third way of looking at
mik somebody ask you where did Mike come
from and you say he was born from his
mom you know and he lives in Arizona and
and and I hear him talking because he
got in a car and he made it across the
road here okay and not because the seeds
in my mind are going off every word of
the Lama Christie really likes to she
loves this thing about uh which I turned
her on to one day when you turn the page
what you see is Flowing from your own
mind
you wrote the book that I'm teaching you
okay and in essence the rest of any book
is blank pages until you turn it and
then your mind lays down the word you
see it's very interesting you are
producing this book as we go you are
throwing Stepping Stones down on the
ground and then stepping on them it's
cool okay
you this book will change according to
whether you guys do yoga
tomorrow okay what this book says will
change according to whether you do your
practice
tomorrow okay it's very interesting if
you if you don't do your
practice uh it'll say something less
interesting because you're writing it
okay it's very interesting okay
uh but then he says something he says
um I'll ask you a question and this is a
theme that he's going to get into now
when you are just looking at the guy in
the mirror and shaving his
face which we said was okay right that's
a pman that's a correct perception
That's
Mike but would you say that any part of
that perception is infected by the
third yeah okay all right got it to some
extent every perception even that I'm
just shaving Mike's face and no one's
asked me yet where he came from
okay nobody's getting philosophical they
just said did you shave this morning D
Michael I said yes you know you can feel
I shaved this morning and then they say
but they don't ask me did your face
where did your face come from okay just
mik was Mike in the mirror yes is that
State of Mind infected by
the Yeah necessarily okay to some extent
it's always that's what he's saying here
okay means it also infects the other
state of mind okay so even an innocent
perception which is valid and correct
that Mike is in the mirror getting
shaved is
infected by a belief that he's not
coming from me okay right and that what
happens to him is not produced by by the
amount of kindness or meanness I show to
others all right
it infects even our what they call uh
nominal perceptions okay uh conventional
perceptions but to but
to
isolate from the Shaving the face
perception
the the percentage of it which believes
that the face came from out
there is is almost like trying to
separate milk out of
water okay like you some part of your
perception is
infected by believing that that that
that mic is coming from himself and not
from seeds in my
mind but to separate the those two
states of mine you know to say this
percentage of my mind was okay it was
just getting shap and this percentage of
my mind thought that Mike was coming
from
himself okay to separate those two minds
which are always intertwined at any
given moment is extremely
difficult it's not as if it's very clear
at any given moment that a part of your
mind is actively mistaken okay it's not
clear even after you've been trained
about emptiness to isolate the part of
your mind which is thinking the wrong
way is very difficult
okay you must become Adept at learning
to distinguish between the okay
perception of Might and the not okay
perception of mind okay otherwise you go
to some extreme otherwise you you you
make you know you could say nothing
matters or nothing's real or something
like that okay so is Mike
teaching
yeah is he speaking
word
[Music]
yeah is the content of what he's
speaking coming from his
thoughts no okay you've just you've just
uh soor J you've just uh distinguished
between the okay two okay perceptions
right is Mike up there yes is he
speaking yes is what he's saying coming
from him no okay and and then you have
to separate those two those two
perceptions right you have to get good
at that the content is coming from
me okay what the content is coming from
me is he there yes what's going on is
coming from me
okay whe I mean it's a great uh if when
you teach
this and mainly I'm concerned that this
week you learn to teach the poster okay
if anybody leaves this Camp without
being able to teach the poster I'd be
really pissed off okay now I mean I want
you to run out and go to the Yoga Yoga
Center in Sacramento and say you know I
could give three nights a really
interesting talks look I got this poster
you know no it's like that it's like
Wheel of Life or something it's so cool
to show up at a yoga studio and say I'm
going to give three nights of free talks
I'll get you more people to take yoga
here you can get them on a monthly
membership or something I'm not charging
you anything I'll give three nights of
free talks I got this sexy you know
ancient Tibetan poster about how to
meditate and you should think like that
this week okay think about how you're
going to go to the Center in Houston you
know I want you to think that way and I
want it to go down in the next month or
two okay but you you you can't do that
responsibly unless you're scribbling
notes all over the poster as we go okay
uh but I I really really want to hear
that you know 150 people went and taught
the meditation poster I wanted to be uh
what do you call Abby Hoffman wrote a
book when I was in a college called the
steal this book it was so fun we used to
go to bookstores and steal it and uh
yeah I want you to do that you know I
want to see this poster everywhere this
top secret Tibetan ancient meditation
post I want everyone to steal it without
asking me and uh print them and teach
them okay all right that's my hope so
put that put your mind in that frame for
the next week you know like how would I
teach that you no I think I'd leave out
the elephant's yamaka thing or you know
you decide okay
you decide
[Music]
okay we have in our mind a
tendency this today's subject
Okay I hold up the pen the minute you
see the pen
you already have some feeling that is
coming from
itself it's it's it's it's ingrained in
your mind for countless billions of
years okay if if you really understand
past lives for countless billions of
years you have looked at pens and said
they are coming from their own side and
now you have you
know that's a tsunami coming at
Amsterdam right and there's this guy
with this whole finger in the hole like
there's a tsunam there's a 100ft tsunami
drawing close to the wall and here's you
with your finger in the hole in the wall
you know like I'm going to stop the
tsunami you know I'm going to start to
see the pen in a different way you're
working against billions of lifetimes of
of wrong idea okay
so even in your dreams says
P you you are still even in dreams when
you see objects you take them to be
coming from the objects even in your
dream
even in your dreams because it's
billions of years of
conditioning when you stop thinking that
way the billions of years will end and
you will take on a different form of
life like someone coming out of a
cocoon like the difference between a
worm and a butterfly you know stop that
one way of thinking and you will evolve
into a higher life form you know called
an ARA okay and it's a beautiful it's
amazing okay Planet B person all right
and and you will be as different from a
from a planet a person as you as a
butterfly is from a worm
right now he gets into an interesting
subject you see we're constantly Even in
our dreams when you hold up an object
the mind immediately believes that it's
coming from its side right immediately
instinctively more than
instinctively almost as part and parcel
of the mind you believe the thing is
coming this way from the object right to
catch yourself doing that is really
hard like I have to sit here and say
this is a pen could it be a boy you know
uh who's right the dog or the
person you know and then and then I have
to say if I put it here and take all the
dogs out of the room all the people out
room what happens it's nothing okay so
is it coming this way or is it coming
this way and then everybody in the room
says oh it must be coming this way you
so I said oh that seeds in your mind
because you gave a pen to somebody else
in the past put a SE in your mind that's
ripening and you see a pen get it yeah
then I hold up the pen and everybody's
like WI
you
know okay it's like that okay then how
do you cat yourself doing it you see
it's so subtle it's so
instantaneous it it must happen a
microsc after the visual Consciousness
but we can't catch it it's probably
165th of a second after the visual
Consciousness you see a certain object
and then there's this percentage of the
mind that believes it's coming this way
automatic it's automatic okay how do you
catch yourself doing it but Bon says put
yourself under
dur put yourself under
dur because then it's more obvious
what's happening okay he'll explain all
right put yourself into a dangerous or
frightening situation or a very
emotional
situation and the degree to which this
thing it looks like it's coming from
itself will increase exponentially and I
ain't talking about pens I'm talking
about Mike and Darcy and whoever
okay then it'll be easier to
catch all right cuz it's so big you know
you're stupid no I'm not then that eye
is pretty big okay all right so he's
going to suggest
that but when someone either Praises you
highly or what do you call what's the
opposite CRI criticizes you
[Music]
strongly some kind
of either happiness
or
right then for a brief period the the
mic that's coming from himself will will
kind of announce himself big time like
that's a good time to catch
yourself feeling that there's a mic
coming from might okay all right when
when you're very happy or you're very
upset in in cases of emotional what do
you
call stress or what's the
opposite High emotion in in situations
of high emotion that the wrong sense of
me inflates and then that's a good time
to catch yourself doing it all right
here we
go so suppose somebody comes up to you
and says uh you know we figured out who
stole
the The Liberation in my hand's books
from the bookstore this morning and you
say really who is it they say you you
know totally what do you call it
un unfounded did you say it yeah totally
unfounded accusation okay that's what
we're talking
about you get get very upset you know
and you
say means it wasn't me I don't have any
what do you
call uh fault or guilt or I don't know
it wasn't me okay guil not it's not I'm
not to blame I'm I cannot be accused I
wasn't even near the Centennial whatever
it is I wasn't even near the place this
morning I was sleeping even during the
meditation class I was sleeping
okay then you get
upset it wasn't me it wasn't
me you can try to prevent yourself from
feeling that but it's gonna it's gonna
burst out
okay so the person who's being accused
of stealing the books from the bookstore
and
[Music]
who's the guy who's wrongly accused and
the me who is not at fault right who is
not culpable
okay means from the from the very depths
of your heart okay SW lingling s say
lingling lingling lingling mean
things uh like that you know that that
mic is coming at you like you know Ling
Ling means w okay like that mic is
like over what you
call it uh like a big wave it's yeah it
just washes over you okay this Big M who
the mik was accused and the mik was
innocent these two these two m big these
big two marks come to you okay got
it that's
the dancing
before that's the gcha dancing before
you put yourself in a situation where
you are wrongly
accused or your partner saying some bad
thing to you you know and and you your
anger
arises and then there's this
big
illusory
me who's the victim you see mean and and
then the one you have to
defend you know the one who's been
wronged you know gets very big so in
those circumstances you can take the
opportunity to examine the gaka the gaka
will be in your face linging that's a
good translation maybe okay uh s the
this is
interesting so he says maybe if you are
really a serious practitioner you could
put yourself purposely into situations
that that either brought on great fear
or great pleasure and then you know like
someone's telling you oh you did a great
job we we never had an event organizer
like you and everybody gives you a big
Applause and then this big Rebecca shows
up and then uh so put yourself in
situation either of being praised or
being criticized like purposely put
yourself in those
situations I think I'd rather be in the
praised one right okay
and then you can check him out then you
can check that mic out you know is he
coming from himself or from somebody
else what would it mean in a case where
somebody accused you of stealing the
books from the
bookstore and this big Mike showed up
who was innocent right this strong
strong feeling of Mike showed up who was
innocent how could you deflate
him how would you how could you wipe
away the
Goa
H yeah exactly
exactly okay he cannot stand up under
that analysis that's a very famous
emptiness language he he cannot stand up
under that kind of analysis you see a
Mike who is truly
innocent meaning who has never accused
anyone else of something of doing
something who that they weren't at fault
uh right try to find that one okay try
to find a mic who's being accused who
never accused anybody else of
anything and then suddenly that big mic
melts then the gcha is is G got it the
gaka is
gar okay because gaka means the thing
you got to
Gar okay gaka means the thing you got
to oh what do you call
like uh melt or disprove
or
H yeah or something I don't know make
disappear
eradicate but it's more like something
that was never there you see it's like
it's refute okay it's kind of a big
word what did I do with the mouse when I
saw the leap
you see you find a verb for that that's
what it is he just I Disappeared
him okay like that that's God okay where
were
we okay now cool so uh put yourself in
situations where where this
self-existent mik was not coming from
something I did it's being
uh wrongly accused or or where he's
being praised lavishly put yourself in
situations like that well I'm trying all
the time but it doesn't
happen
uh put purposely put yourself in a
situation like that and then deflate
that mic by understanding that he's
coming from having done the same thing
to somebody else before right it's just
a perception forced on me by something I
did to someone else before and then that
might gets pretty well deflated okay
right actually any praise you
encounter in your life is due to
something you did six months
ago and you could do the same action and
people would be criticizing you if you
had criticized somebody else in the past
it has nothing to do with with how good
action you just did you know that
sometimes you do something really good
and everybody criticizes you something
sometimes you do something really bad
and they're all like you're really
cool okay it doesn't relate to what you
did it relates to what you what you said
to somebody six months ago okay uh once
you can think that way then it's hard to
get up in front of a bunch of people and
have them praise you and think you're
you're
cool okay then you don't worry about it
so
much
done no okay he gives a really good
example how are you gonna catch yourself
misunderstanding
yourself how are you going to catch
yourself misunderstanding yourself he
says let's take an
example two people are walking down a
path side by side especially here okay
over the ice okay side by
side you are
you are focusing on your friend you're
having a conversation right so you're
focusing on the friend but you're
also one part of your mind is watching
the ice patches unless you want to fall
in your butt okay so so really two
things are going your your attention is
split you're you're talking to your
friend but you're you're always going
like this you know to see if you're
going to hit one of those speed hunts
right uh so your your attention you one
part of your mind is is attending to
this the condition of the p and one and
then most of your mind is attending to
your discussion with your friend
[Music]
okay
so put yourself in situations where you
might be able to catch yourself seeing
things wrong due to the emotional
intensity either High Praise or high
criticism going on okay put yourself in
situations where that's going down okay
and
then with a with a subtle corner of your
thoughts see if you can catch your other
part of your mind see if you can catch
it thinking that that the me is coming
from
himself see see if you can see if a
little part of your own mind can catch
the rest of your mind thinking that you
are coming from
yourself which is in fact the only way
you can get upset about being blamed for
something if if if you weren't looking
at yourself if Mike wasn't looking at
Mike wrong Mike couldn't get upset by
someone blaming him for something
because if he was looking at Mike the
right way he would understand that if
Mike got blamed for something it was
because Mike blamed somebody else before
and the only natural intelligent
reaction to being blamed would be to
stop blaming other people in the future
and you wouldn't be thinking at all
about the person who was blaming you
because that doesn't do
anything
okay which the net result is you're nice
all the
time okay like my L used to say even if
all is be us the worst thing that can
happen is you'll just be nice all the
time
okay I'll run it by you one more time
because I I need it for myself which is
why you let me be here
um someone blames someone blames me for
something then a a an empty ner person
automatically thinks the first thought
is oh who did I blame in the last few
weeks you know
and then their second thought is four
powers and then their third thought is
power number three and then their next
thought is I should stop blaming other
people and that's the extent of the
conversation the conversation never goes
to why is this person blaming me cuz you
know why they're blaming you okay and
there's no reaction to the other person
because you don't have time to react
with them and think all these other
thoughts then by the time you have time
to react to them there's no sense to
react to them because you already have a
plan you have a game plan I'll stop
blaming other people and this person
will go
away and and the conversation is
over okay then the worst that can happen
is you stop blaming other people and if
there's no such thing as karma you just
become a nicer
person okay all
right easy to say impossible to do okay
this is
interesting
uh he
says you know he he advised us that a
certain corner of our mind should be
observing how the rest of our mind
believes that might comes from himself
son okay so a corner of our mind should
be observing the rest of the Mind and
observing how wrong they are it is and
believing that things are coming from
their own side okay then he says an
interesting thing P he's very very very
subtle you will never see anything like
this in any other Buddhist scripture he
is unbelievably subtle it means he must
have been practicing it all the time you
know but he says you know in my
experience don't let the examining mind
get too big use a corner of your mind
but don't use half your mind or three
corners of your mind because you then
you'll lose it because then too much of
your mind is
correct okay like don't overdo
it okay let the other part of the Mind
be
screwy you know don't don't like
convince him right away let him
misunderstand stuff so you can watch him
misunderstand stuff okay but don't
understand too much because then he
won't misunderstand anymore and there
won't be anything to
watch okay it's kind of cool kind of
cool um you said
TK TK to what's
Tok yeah be skillful you know be be uh
what do you call be skillful in watching
yourself because if you're too right
there won't be anything to watch okay
and means what mama
mama
Point uh that's a big that's a very
important point
Gin Gin is very very colloquial you
won't find in any dictionary it means
uh in the act of happening so nin means
as it's appearing to you as your mind is
misunderstanding try to catch try to
catch it in the ACT what you say in the
ACT while it while that wrong mic is
appearing to you try to catch it
okay
so sometimes that mic will show
up uh coming from your body sometimes
that mic will show up coming from your
mind okay what's that
mean
uh sometimes you'll look at your body
and say there's might coming from
M there's I I look at my body and I say
it's I I if it's flesh out there by the
way you might as well commit suicide
okay because you can't change it you can
go through the rest of your life or you
can just end it right if it's coming if
it's coming from its side there's no
there's nothing you can do it'll just
get old and it will kill you you so my I
think you should got to have a couple
beers and then just jump off a bridge or
something okay and my brother did I know
you know so you can but you look at your
body and and you can catch yourself
thinking my body is coming from my
body and you can also look at your
thoughts and think that my thoughts are
coming from my
thought
but that's not the main thing we're
worried about okay looking at your body
and it comes from the body thinking
about your thoughts and thinking they're
coming from the thoughts that's not the
big that's not the big one that we're
working on what is
more more importantly this is getting
hard and it's hot in here and you're
getting sleepy
okay I think
yeah the worst thing for concentration
is heat in my mind uh I freeze people
and they all like complain afterwards
it's okay
uh this is tough okay are you your are
you your
body are you your body
no no are you your
mind now careful are you your mind and
body
together that's a difficult one you know
I I remember uh Janice what's your name
bradden what's her
name yeah what's your mom's name Carmen
what's her real name chin yeah chiny so
uh chin la
one of the one the first student of
kriy like in
1970 something 72 or something very
first student so she had a child and
uh and then she used to bring the child
to class the way that AA brings Bella to
class sometimes so she was like 5 years
old and I remember we came out of this
class and I'm like I saw her you know in
the kitchen cuz she had to sent the
kitchen and then I went in I said Janice
I got a question for you and she said
yes and I said are you your body and she
said no and then I said are you your
mind and she said no I said are you your
body and your mind together she said of
course what else I am I'm every you know
that's all of me that's all there is my
body plus my mind is who I am you know I
was
[Music]
like so don't say it so easily don't say
no so easily aren't you aren't you all
your physical parts and all your mental
Parts pasted together isn't that
you I don't what's wrong with saying
that
huh yeah so here's a delicate thing okay
be
careful you could have separate sheets
of Tibetan text you could have a back
cover and a front cover and you could
have the the clock okay
but to somebody what do they call those
kind of people autistic I think is it
autistic they have conceptual problems
they can't glue things together the way
most of us do understand me they
couldn't see these three things as one
thing all they would see would be pages
and covers and a clock but they wouldn't
think
book okay they could see parts but they
can't see the whole somehow okay which
proves
something the book is not only its part
the book is also the state of mind which
synthesizes the parts into a whole
without that state of mind it's not a
book then it's just pieces of stuff you
see there has to be a fourth element
here the pages the covers the cloth and
the thought that it's a book and that
the mind which puts the three together
and that a book because maybe a
different state of mind could could look
at this table and see these two cloths
together and say there are two beautiful
cloths and they wouldn't consider the
orange cloth part of the blue they would
consider it rather part of the alter
cloth you see your mind decides where
the lines are drawn and and for those of
us in this room having offered others
literary educations in the past we see
it as a book but it's not in the pages
and it's it's not in the cover and it's
not in the cloth that's coming from your
mind that's a synthetic image that you
are you are encasing the pieces with and
without that it wouldn't be a book so
are you your mind and your body
together you could say not only H that
until tell you think of yourself as
yourself it's just meat and thought
okay there has to be something which
ties them together synthesizes them into
mind which is done by the mind and not
from their side there's nothing
inherently connected between this me and
those St you see it's a perception
somebody's tying them together and call
them M okay they are not mik by
themselves without the synthesizing H
they're just part okay why are we
talking about that
uh yeah
dang
Mach so listen listen carefully
okay we just talked about how it's a
it's a mental process in your own mind
that's gluing the meat and the thoughts
together and calling it might okay it's
it's a it's a concept coming out of your
own mind which is gluing put together
this meat and those thoughts and calling
it the package he's calling the package
M okay that people who don't think that
people who haven't thought about that
look at the arm think about the thoughts
and think that must be
M it's it's where we got stuck about 3
minutes
ago okay when that's that if I say is
the meat and the thoughts M and you say
yes you're flirting with the gaka you're
somewhere close to the gaka you're
somehow thinking this me and these
thoughts were mik
automatically before anybody thought of
them as mik got it they are yelling
mik they are in they are by themselves
mik whether I think of them as Mike or
not okay that's gaka then you're near
the gaka the human tendency is to take
the collection of parts
and believe that that's the thing before
the Mind thinks of them as that which is
the last part that you need you don't
have all the parts of a person until you
have the state of mind that's gluing
them all together got it so is your mind
and your body might no well what is mind
my mind and my body and the thought to
think of
them okay then that's the whole mind and
that's the real mic that mic is
there why does thinking of mic that way
make a difference what's the
point why
bother why throw that last thing into
mik well isn't it is it wrong to think
that Mike is just his body and his
mind yeah because because if I
understand that thinking of Mike
thinking of the meat and thoughts as
Mike is also part of Mike if I
understand that then I can change
then M can change M can change from
Mortal to
Immortal M can change to someone who's
pretty frequently criticized so someone
who is rarely
criticized which would be
nice
okay all right J that's me they you're
you're hanging in there very well I
really admire you okay I know everyone's
totally burned out from especially the D
mountain people are basket cases
uh and I'm impressed
okay the China people are a little bit
better but not much
okay means now you've got chuk May means
no boo boo you really got the mic now
you got the mic who's not the mic who's
the mic that's not the mic the mic is
just Mike's body and M without somebody
thinking of them as mic
why thinking of them as
M due to the relative amount of kindness
they have paid to others in the past
okay that's always has to be the punch
line due to the relative amount of
kindness they paid to others in the past
which is forcing me to think a mic as
M if it's a good mic I did I was nice
down of people if it's a bad mic I was
mean to of people you got to put in
those last lines or else Peter's thing
doesn't matter because the last part is
what means I can change
M
okay
uh means it's a
CCH it's
easy okay it's easy what they
got what's
that they stop it okay stop
what the wrong mic the mic who should
not have been blamed there's no such
thing the Mich was wrongly
blamed who didn't deserve to be blamed
is there such a thing there's no such
thing okay got it put your mind on the
mic who didn't deserve to be blamed you
got
it he never existed there's no such
thing you always deserve what you get
okay okay no that's gaka that's you want
an easy gaka Le you want a
leaa the Michu didn't deserve to be
blamed the Mich was unjustly blamed
there's no justice that he was blamed
can you find one like that no it's all
world the universe is perfectly just
people get really upset when I say that
you know when it finally Dawns on them
that there's a perfect Justice to life
it's very irritating you know like I
created that person in my life yes you
mean every detail yes you mean even the
way they talk
yes that sucks you
know yeah okay so if you want a easy
form of the
gaka think of the you who didn't deserve
the last you
know harm that someone did you that's
the
gcha the Nick who didn't deserve to be
criticized by the last person who
criticized him is the
gaka this is
cool because we're playing with a gaka
that makes a difference you know then
Nick will be more interested in not
criticizing others rather than being
interested in being upset at someone is
criticizing him wrongly because there's
no such
person okay and then he saves so much
time he just concentrate on being nice
to other people and then the whole the
whole mental space of Defending yourself
against what unjust
criticism is is stop you save all that
disc what do you call hard dis bace you
know the no the Mind remove 50% of the
stuff from a computer which is filled to
97% capacity right how fast it goes it's
the same with the Mind throw out the 50%
of your mind time that's spent on uh
defending yourself from unjust there's
no unjust criti in and then and then
suddenly the hard dis is moving so fast
because you just recovered half your
mind time yeah and you're happy okay
it's really fun okay all
right what time am I supposed to
step no
way you GNA make them die yeah 3:30 okay
here we go can you hang in there you all
right you're like saving the world right
now okay whether you're it like two
years from now you go boing I get
it all
right
uh this is a delicate Point
okay if you don't get what we just went
through
correct and someone says what what's the
gcha you will either overestimate it or
underestimate it right you will
either say that too few things are the
gcha or you'll say too many things are
the gcha for example is there a
Nick yeah yeah if you don't understand
emptiness well you would say there's no
Nick okay all right that then the the
extent of the gaka got too big that's
what they're talking about they're
talking about the extent of the gcha in
your mind
how how widespread is the gacha in your
mind does it cover everything and you a
wise one should say no well who doesn't
it cover Nick Nick who the Nick who's
face I was shaving in the mid he's there
I mean I cut him this morning okay he's
there that then you say then you say uh
the Nick who got caught you know uh was
it the was it that it was all lousy res
there was it that it was an old razor
blade and then the wise one will say
no uh it was that I I HT someone and
that's why the razor blade was dull this
morning
okay that person you see the person who
says um how you
saying if you say the razor blade was
dull so it cut me then your estimate of
the extent of the gja is too small
okay you got to widen it up a bit it
also
includes dull razor blades gaka also
includes D razor blade but doesn't
include Nick no so get it the right
extent of the gaka don't make it too fat
don't make it too skinny okay and and
the the trick is to get the gcha just
the right
we okay is Nick there yes okay so the GJ
is not too big what's the razor blade
thull and is that what cut you
no good then it's not too small then
we're also threw the we also threw the
razor blade into the stuff with gaka
okay got it all right
[Music]
if you're unable to identify the Nick
that doesn't exist he will continue to
appear to
you
who I didn't do anything
wrong okay the nicku is unjustly blamed
okay if you can't identify that
non-existent thing it will continue to
harass you okay then you'll be always
defending yourself right
uh Dr
Char but if you're able to identify the
Nick who's not there which one was
that then the Nick who was wrongly
accused like unjustly accused I like
unjustly because everything is perfectly
just the word unjust shouldn't
exist
okay somebody said a cute thing the
other day said this is totally
irrelevant okay they said but it was so
cute they said we have no choice but to
accept free will
uh I was like
okay
uh
uh but the Nick who is not Nick is
always hiding in
Nick that the Nick that we see okay so
the Nick who is UN justly accused is
always hanging out around Nick for for
people we we can see that it's there
potentially if we understand the docta
you know we can always misunderstand
Nick the Nick
who was unjustly accused is always close
to
Nick for people who understand meaning
they they can catch themselves easily it
they see that they could make an easy
mistake under pressure
all this philosophy goes down the drain
under pressure okay I was in India
during the oil what do you call it
embargo thing and
uh they we couldn't get anything uh I
was in Dara and uh a what do you call a
kerosene truck would come once a week so
you know I was cooking on my own and uh
we're talking a uh what do you
call what you call those things
colan a single burner colan thing you
know that's all every family had and I
had one and I depended on it to eat you
know cuz I had to cook my own F bread
and everything so in that little thing
and then you know I'm like I ran out of
kosene you know and they said don't
worry there's a truck coming on Friday I
went down lower DM Sala and uh there was
like 2,000 people waiting for the truck
and then the truck came and
uh and everybody people were kicking
biting pushing you know old women were
being trod trod into the ground and I
was like freaked out you know I was like
21 or something I'm like you know I'm
American you know I I'm civilized I I
wouldn't do that you know then I spent
one week without bread one week without
rice you know next
week I was the tallest guy there
I got my
gu and uh so Under Pressure all this
philosophy goes out the window you know
like you can blame Nick to a certain
extent you know but blame him for the
broken pip then it's too much then then
he'll get upset you know he'll forget
about the the the unjustly blame Nick
that didn't Nick that didn't exist okay
okay um
and what you can do is put yourself in
situations where you explore that border
you can purposely put yourself in
situations to explore you know and
strengthen your your view put yourself
in situations where you are bra for
things that you never even get close to
and don't tell anybody and just explore
how you
feel because you couldn't even be blamed
in a self planned way if you hadn't CRI
got okay all
right
Chik take yourself to the edge of a
cliff there's a nice one in China called
the
uman have you been
toan yeah then there you you go up and
there's a there's a straight Cliff it
goes down like a mile and Buddhists used
to go up there and
jump and they there was a tradition that
you would go to Nirvana and you wouldn't
then hit they never found the body you
know so me and Christie went up there to
see it you know and I'm standing on the
edge and I'm like if she tells me to
jump am I going to jump you know if she
says let's jump am I going to jump you
know I was
like I was like I was like kept talking
to her look there's cotton candy around
[Laughter]
and
uh yeah I got
off take yourself to the edge of a cliff
like that it's really frightening it's
like a mile straight
down she jo
say a kind of
Terror will rise in your heart like I'm
gonna I'm about to fall I might fall
people were playing at the edge there
was no like Gat or
you know people are these kids are
teenagers were like taking photos ha
like at that moment you don't think oh
Michael's body might fall or Michael's
mind might fall okay you don't make
these distinctions you say what I might
fall okay
so your mind is is
holding this is I have a little I'm not
sure about this part okay I'm really not
sure about this part anyway I'll present
it
but anyway okay let's go
uh
rather there is a a mic
who is
somehow mixed up with body and mind in
the way that water is mixed with milk
okay
indivisibly mixed there's a mic mixed
into body and mind are mixed and there's
a mic there okay and and then you think
that mic shouldn't fall okay but to me
that's sort of flirting with the correct
view of it you see so I'm not quite
comfortable with that
okay you are
the the mic that really is mic is a mic
that is
uh sythesized from body and mind okay
there's don't do that there's a body and
there's a mind and there's a mic that's
synthesized from the body
mind
uh I I think rather it might be this
okay if if you're thinking of the mic
that the synthesis came from yourself
that would be correct VI if you're
thinking of a mic that's body and mind
mixed together and there's some kind of
mic there you could say soul maybe then
that's a wrong view okay so there's a
good synthesis and a wrong synthesis
how's that one is coming from you and
one was always there and the one that
was always there doesn't exist and when
you're about to fall off a cliff you're
grabbing to the one that was always
there which is not there which is the
Nick which is unjustly accused
okay uh Jing
sah
[Music]
sorry
sorry so when you're watching a horse
race by you don't say look the horse's
body is racing by and you don't say look
the horse's mind is racing by you just
say horse so you synthesized the horse
from the body and mind of a thing okay
juding there's the there's the clarifier
okay a horse which was synthesized not
by
you okay a horse which was
naturally a horse from the horse's body
and the horse's mind but wasn't that way
because you thought of it in that way
okay a horse which was put together for
from body and mind but not because you
offered someone a horse before
okay got
it is there a body is there a horse's
body yes is there a horse's mind yes are
they necessarily related to each other
but from their own side no no you see it
takes your thought to make them that way
okay but to think that they are
connected from their own side is is
wrong okay they weren't naturally
connected they're connected because you
think of that
way people who are crazy or people who
are
geniuses people who are
artistic or people who are Thomas Edison
they look at stuff and they don't see it
the way we do and they don't separate
the part PE they don't separate things
the way we do I draw a line between the
orange cloth and the white cloth you
know Thomas Edison is looking at a piece
of thread and seeing something that
would light up all the cities of America
and he's not seeing a threat he's not
Drawing the Line the same way we do uh
it's it's it's difficult because we're
in the middle of doing that you know the
way in which you what do you call that
in English
conceptualize
demarc is uh
subjective there's nothing to say that
the horse body and the horse's mind
belong to the horse until you think of
it that way okay
all
right yeah two great Monastery what does
s
mean h what does mean rice pile and we
all know that hail destroys a pile of
rice
then a dong monk will say and then the
hail
melts and all that's left is the pile of
right that's an old debate thing
okay then if you take all the buildings
in one of those great monasteries right
dukong means
the the temple in which you hold your
prayers together
and taba means the monks okay so if you
don't
uh if you don't uh make a fine
distinction so what we're doing with
horses and what we're doing with Nicks
we are also doing with SAS and
dles okay we are feeling
that there's a there's a
synthesis of all the monks in Sarah and
all the houses and and temples and sah
that we lump them all together and call
them Sarah and we think somehow that's a
natural lumping and that it's not
something coming from us okay people go
to Sarah in India okay people go to
Sarah by the way Sarah Lai wrote me a
couple weeks ago which is rather
extraordinary Lai means the governing
Council of both cers okay and they said
would you and your students help
organize a tour of America by our
monks so I'm going to write them back
and say not if they're going to do those
bogus
dances but uh but if you sing yesi too
convince him to teach ma Mika then we
would
probably like we'll do a tour or he can
come to New York for 10 days and teach
Majik then we would do that you know so
I'm gonna call them and tell them that
but anyway
why is there a sari Lai means the
governing Council of both s why is there
a
sari as there's two
SAS there's s May and there SRA J it's
two monasteries in a single enclosure
and there's a green
line okay and you don't walk over the
green line you know like and the green
line goes like this you got to know this
is houses on their side and this house
is on our side you know and you don't
there's them and there's us s is always
better in the debate okay than sah J
people who they have some genetical
problems uh so
anyway
uh that's why there's a sanii to go you
know somebody has to organize when a
pipe goes under one of those houses like
that it won't get you know
anyway
uh why did I say that yeah so you a
newcomer PE folks come from the US
they come they say you say where did you
go they say I went to see Shri Babi
Joyce in my and then I took the bus to
bopi and went to Sarah and you say which
Sarah and they look at you like what
what do you mean and you're like well
which Sarah did you go to and they say I
went to Sarah you know and they don't
understand there's two Setters there you
see so saying that all the monks in a
place and all the temples in a place are
one Monastery is coming from you
and that's an example because there's
two monasteries and no one would ever
know if you didn't live there you see
they're completely separate Mon and
they're interlocking you know that it
looks like what do they call that map
when a politician Jerry Mander it's a
Jerry Mander thing okay there's two mon
there but but it it's not in the place
and it's not in the monks it's a concept
placed on the place by the people who
live there okay and someone new who
shows up sees it as one Monastery so is
it one or is it two is it a chew toy or
is it a pen you see what I mean you're
trying to he's trying to get you into
the mood that even monasteries are also
constructs of your mind forced upon you
by your past Karma okay all right here
we go
Kupa means what's like in
Kya
huh that's
K yeah the the word of the Buddha it
means the word capital
T what's
ch ch not ch
Chu is water what's Chu 10 yes K means
10 scriptures and that's what they call
a g at mon okay they're called a 10
Booker means they've mastered 10 five
ancient Indian works and their
commentaries okay so they don't call
them gashes they call them kupas okay 10
Bookers all right
uh people mistake the collection of the
parts of that Tash GES as being the
tashes
okay all right they look at the parts of
those
people and they take them to be those
people they look at the at the sum total
I like sum total let's use that
they look at the sum total of the parts
of those GES and call them and think
that's what the G is but it's not what's
missing thinking of them as a
gash which is not voluntary it's forced
on you by your past Karma okay it's
forced on you by your by your seed you
believe the pen is a pen and you get
upset when the dog destroys it and chews
it right okay
because you you believe it should have
been a
pen by itself and it's not it's only a
pen because you're seeing it as a
t got it you're seeing the G as a
g and until tell you see him as a gashi
he not a gashi he's just somebody's head
and somebody's legs and somebody's mind
okay gashi aren't GES okay kupas AR
kupas all right
the point he's trying to make is under
under analysis it would seem to be that
all the parts of a car together are the
car and it would seem reasonable to say
that the sum total of the parts of a car
is the car but that's wrong and you're
you're flirting with gcha when you think
that because it's not a car until you
put all the tires there all the axles
there all the windshield and the other
parts there and then your Karma forces
you to see it as a car because without
the last thing you won't see it as a
car get
it it's very hard it's very hard okay
why make that distinction who cares it's
just a car whether you understand how
you're seeing it you can still drive
it but it will
break and it will work
I I would say you could even debate
whether it's a
c got it an unri liable car
is I say it's not a
car he said it's
liability you got to get used to that
that's the last thing I'll say okay
uh you are living in a world where
nothing works for reliably or
predictably you know you undertake uh to
earn some money or you undertake to do
yoga and you don't know that you will
not lose money or or break your neck and
there's people who have broken their
necks in yoga right so you undertake
actions in your world on your planet you
undertake
actions as a gambling it's a form of
gambling I read a book by
uh the chairman of Sony I think it
was and he said uh he didn't invest in
stocks because it was no different from
gambling you know uh he just felt there
was no difference and no nobody can tell
if the Stock's going to go up tomorrow
or not nobody in the world can tell no
matter how well trained they are they
can't tell so there's no difference
between that and going to a Castle Rock
Casino over in Sedona and throwing some
money on the wheel you know uh it's just
their glorified gambling
people but that's what you're doing all
the time you're you're just gambling
that what you try is going to work and
then I I sometimes I sit there and I I I
worry about it and I say well why do
people do that why do you think people
do that why do people get a job that
they're not sure if it's going to make
any money or
not why do people buy a car when they're
not sure if it's going to break tomorrow
or not why do people buy aspirin knowing
that half of the pills won't
work why do people put up with that
would you if you went to the
store and you went to the buy a Loa of
bread and you went to the what do you
call it the bakery section right and
there was uh all these Lo plastic bags
with half loaves of bre bread in them
would you pay the full would you buy it
if it had been opened and half the bread
taken out would you buy it you just
wouldn't do it because there's a certain
standard in your mind you know a loaf of
bread should be 35 slices of bread and
not half of them taken out that's not a
loaf of bread you have a certain uh what
do you call it standard for what a loaf
of bread is and if someone had all these
loaves of bread even if it was on sale
you know somebody took half the pieces
out but we'll sell you the rest you just
wouldn't buy it you know but you buy all
this other stuff you buy aspin half of
them don't work you go to jobs that you
might lose money at you know you eat and
drink things that might cost cancer you
know
I
why why buy a car that that you don't
know if it's going to break tomorrow
it's very frightening for me somebody
said uh G I'll give you my car I've got
this old boo it
works you know and then they're like
we'll give you this car and I'm like
we'll give it to you for free the mle
houses they said we'll give you our van
for free and I'm like I didn't know what
to do we had this big crisis right
uh it this big crisis and I'm like what
if it breaks tomorrow then it's worse
than a than my vvo and then I realized I
didn't know if it was going to break
tomorrow but I didn't know if the Volvo
was going to break tomorrow you know but
the Volvo's been running for 300,000
miles but normally older cars break
first you know I I got all screwed up I
wish they hadn't offered it to me
[Laughter]
why so my last question you have one
minute to answer why why do you put up
with
that why don't you just buy usand at
work I think yeah what makes sense and
I'm not blaming you for anything no just
no he said correctly I believe that we
we just early in our life we decide
there's no other choice it's not that
we're stupid or something you know like
if there were an aspirin that all worked
in the bottle we would buy it and we
wouldn't buy the one that have the
aspirin's work and if there were a car
that never
broke I believe it would quickly become
known that this kind of car doesn't
break you know unless there were some
what do you call it difficulty in
perceiving it you see
okay it's very
delicate all right if there were
obviously a car that never broke
everybody would buy that kind of
car unless there was something about
that car that made it almost invisible
to normal people you see and that's
cocka that's cocka okay those cars exist
the kind of car that never breaks
exists we just have some impediment that
we can't uh perceive them okay that's
all all right
and the purpose of this class and the
purpose of the meditation we're learning
is to remove that impediment and then
you
can uh create cards that that never
break how would you create a c that
never
break give rights to
people do you ever give R to people no
is it
enough okay how do you know my car okay
so keep being nice until everything
works all right that's so
simple keep being nice you got to be
more nice than you are now because
things still don't work sometimes
okay as long as things aren't working
all the time you still have to be more
nice okay nicer got
it okay